- Hey folks and welcome to the lesson
on setting up your workspace
for rapid user interface design.
In this lesson, what I'm
gonna talk to you about
is how I would set up my computer
if I had just sat down in the new computer
and knew I was gonna be doing
a lot of design work there.
And so it's just kind
of the little tweaks,
and settings modifications, and
extensions I would download,
and that sort of stuff just to make
the rest of the design
work more efficient.
Now one warning before we get
started is a lot of designers
love to just really noodle on
the details of tool chains,
and workflows, and making
everything 1% more efficient.
I'm really not all about that.
What I want you to do is
breeze through this video,
make some of the changes I recommend here.
But by and large, spend the
vast majority of your time
on actually designing rather than trying
to make your tools perform 2% better.
So with that being said,
let's dive right in.
All right, so I've got
this new project in Figma.
And I'm just gonna kind
of do a little fake design
to show you the things that
I wanna illustrate here.
So the first thing I'm
gonna do is actually paste
in an image that I have on
my clipboard with command, V.
It's a nice, pretty
image of Mount Rainier.
Let's just say this is kind
of some generic website.
Press command, zero to zoom into 100%.
And I'm gonna press R.
That's gonna make a new rectangle
to add a little header here.
So cool, I have a header for my website.
If I can't see it all by the way,
just press command, shift, backslash
and that toggles that left panel.
Gives me a little bit
more visibility here.
Now you'll see that Figma
made this layer gray.
C4C4C4 is the code,
though you don't have to really
worry too much about that.
One thing that I absolutely
recommend doing is open this up.
And here you can see we're picking a color
using the RGB system.
Actually, that's not really
a great way to pick colors.
And in this course I recommend using HSB.
So just pick HSB from the slider.
And basically that's
gonna allow you to specify
four different numbers that represent
whatever color you want.
Now typing in numbers here
is only one of the ways
to specify a color.
Actually, a lot of the time
I can just kind of slide
to the particular color that I want.
And the most common
color that I'm gonna want
for new layers like this is white
which is always gonna be in
the upper left-hand corner
no matter what the particular hue value
that you have here is.
So cool, now I have my white layer.
Of course, if I press R again
and go on to make another rectangle,
it's the same silly gray, C4C4C4.
Again useless, so actually what I wanna do
is select this white layer.
And I'm gonna go to Edit and
say Set Default Properties.
That just means the rest
of the time in this file
when I create a new layer,
it's gonna have a white fill
instead of that gray fill.
Unfortunately in Figma right now,
this setting only works at the file level.
So I will have to change it
again and again if I'm
doing different files.
But if I know I'm gonna
do a lot of design work
in this one file,
it can still be a really
useful thing to do.
Now I'm gonna use command, shift, L
to lock this image layer
'cause I know I won't
need to do anything here.
And nice, I have my header.
If I wanted to do something
like create a button
on a colored background,
I'm most likely to use white.
If I wanted to do something
like let's say maybe
create a card element,
I'll give it a little bit of border radius
and I'll give it a shadow.
And that's more likely than not
gonna be a white background.
So white is just a really useful color
to have as the default here.
Let's say though that
I'm gonna do something
like maybe have a button
on a white background.
Then it's more likely that
I'm gonna wanna use a color.
And now I can pick it either
with the visual color picker
or with this HSP color picker
which we'll go over a lot
more in future lessons.
One other thing related to
color that's worth pointing out
is if you ever export your files
and you notice that the exported file
looks slightly different
than what it looked like
when you were designing it
or maybe it looks different on the web,
it's almost certainly
because your color space
is not set to sRGB.
So if you're using Figma for the web,
sRGB is the default setting.
If you're using it for desktop,
you need to go do that
and it's gonna make you restart your app.
Boom, easy enough to do.
Now just because it's
bugging me a little bit,
I'm gonna go give each of these two layers
a nice little shadow here.
Go into Effects, it's the default one,
but I'm just gonna make the
blur a little bit bigger.
Oftentimes looks just the tad better.
Okay, another thing
that I would probably do
pretty early on in Figma
is get some plugins.
And like I said in the intro,
designers love to talk endlessly
about what plugins are the best
and kind of fiddle with these
and try and optimize endlessly.
I would much prefer you
spend your time designing.
So I'm actually just gonna cover
a couple of these plugins
that are the most useful.
One is Better Font Picker.
I highly recommend this one.
So basically if I make some text,
I press T, click and
drag to do a text box.
Let's say it's My Mountain Odyssey.
If I go to select what font I'm using
from the default Figma font picker,
I can't see what any of these look like.
And so unless I have every
single one memorized and I don't,
that's not very useful.
Better to use the Better Font Picker.
And let's say here I
can see that Adelle Sans
is kind of this nice,
rounded, friendly font here.
So I'll pick that one,
and I'm off to the races.
Of course, I'll make
it a little bit bigger
like a good title guys here, bold it.
And so on.
Another plugin that you'll
see me use is Content Reel.
So Content Reel is really
great if you're generating
let's say something like I wanted
a little profile picture for the author,
and then I'll have the
author's name right here.
And I'll make that a good
body text size, maybe 16.
Well, one thing I can do
with this Content Reel plugin
is if I have a layer selected
that is either an image
or a vector shape that
could become an image,
I can click this Avatars button.
And boom, I'm gonna get avatar
of a person right there.
If I click this full name,
bam, same sort of thing.
What's also cool is you can do this
with many layers at a time.
So if you had a whole list,
I could really quickly
find different avatars
for each of the people on
the list, so that's nice.
I also have a couple of
plugins that are icon-related.
Feather Icons and Material Icons.
So they both kind of work the same way.
Feather Icons is bigger and softer.
Material design is a little bit smaller
and sort of default looking.
But if I say, "Oh, I want a search icon,"
I can just pull that up right here
and double click it.
Boom, it's on my artboard.
If you see the text appear above it,
it means that layer has not recognized
that it actually lives on this frame here.
So I need to drag it out, drag it back in,
and it's good to go.
So now maybe I could do
something like have a search bar.
And it was very easy to create that.
And then finally you
should also download Stark
which can be really good for for instance
looking at the text contrast
between a text color
and a background color.
Of course, black to white is 21:1,
and it says this passes
at all different levels of accessibility
which is a very intricate topic
that we will be getting into
much more later in the course.
Now that's most of what I
would do to modify Figma.
There's also a couple of files
that I would make sure
I had on my computer.
So one of the ways I like to pull them up
is by pressing command, space,
and this brings up Mac's Spotlight search.
If I have this,
then I can for instance
grab my hand pointer cursor.
I'll get this here,
and I can just drag it in super easily.
This is really good for a lot of designs
if you wanna show like for instance
that something is a hover state.
So maybe I have one version
of the button with no hover,
but then I wanna show
the version of the button
when someone hovers it.
Well, this little hand pointer cursor
is a great way to do that.
Likewise, if I wanna have
someone typing into the text box,
I want a text cursor.
So that one is also pretty simple to do.
And if I just want a default cursor
that doesn't really necessarily correspond
to hovering over anything in particular,
the arrow cursor is where it's at.
So I've got that.
All of these files are linked below
so you can download them and use them.
Another thing you'll see
me do pretty frequently
is use a little text expansion.
So you'll see me type things like :abc
which expands into the
alphabet pasted three times.
And the way I'm doing that
is with an app called aText.
aText is fantastic because it allows you
to let's say type in certain things
and have them expand into
certain other things.
So every time I type :abc,
I get the alphabet three times.
Why is that useful for design?
Well, it turns out that
the ideal line length
is typically between about 50
and 75 characters per line.
So in a design if I have
paragraphs and paragraphs of text
and I wanna ensure that they're gonna have
about that line length,
I'll paste in the alphabet three times
which allows me to see
ah yes, this is about as long
as I should have a line be
for this given font and
this given font size.
And this is about as
short as it should be.
And this is mostly applicable
for longer form text.
Speaking of longer form text,
another way that I will use this
is I will say something like :lorem1.
And this brings up one
paragraph of Lorem Ipsum text
which is sort of the default
filler texts that designers use
when they just need to put
some texts in and design.
I have Lorem1, I have Lorem2,
all the way up to Lorem5
which it's a little bit difficult to see,
but that's five paragraphs
of Lorem Ipsum filler text.
Now this can be really useful
just to sort of validate
that the particular design looks good
and works well with longer text.
But one warning is I
actually encourage you
not to use Lorem Ipsum text
too much when you're
really doing a design.
As soon as possible,
try and use realistic text
or even quasi-realistic text
for the particular design
that you're working on.
Just because those particular
words, the subject matter,
even the length of the
sentences that you're typing in
is gonna affect the
whole feel of the design.
And so text is actually an important part
of the feel of the overall design.
That being said, for
illustrating a visual point
or trying to do something very quickly,
there's no problem with
some Lorem Ipsum filler.
Now like I said,
I like to use aText for a text expander.
It's pretty great because it
is a one-time payment of 4.99,
and it also happens to work in Figma.
Not all texts expansion
does work in Figma.
If you are using Sketch or other apps,
it's probably worth trying to see
if the default Mac text expansion works.
So what you can do is open up
the keyboard settings here.
And if you go to Text,
you can add something
like abc and type in-
Well, of course it
replaced it right there.
But you can add in whatever you want
and have it be replaced
with something else.
But just because of complicated details
relating to how Figma is programmed,
this doesn't currently work in Figma.
It does work in Sketch.
While we're on the topic
of keyboard settings,
if you navigate over to Shortcuts here
you can add specific keyboard
shortcuts for different apps
by going to App Shortcuts here
and then pressing the plus button.
So basically you have
to enter the exact name
of the menu command you want to add.
Which if I wanna add a Figma command,
I find that one thing I do all the time
is I like to upper case text.
So Text Upper Case is the
exact name of the menu command.
And if I go to Text Upper Case,
I can then enter in a keyboard shortcut.
I like command, shift, U.
And if I just type command, shift, U,
it formats it properly.
I can press add.
And then whenever I'm in Figma,
I can press command, shift, U,
and automatically uppercase text,
undo it, whatever I want.
Now we've covered Feather Icons
and Material Icons already.
But you should also know
that I have developed
a free set of icons.
It's free for all Learn UI Design students
called Quantum Icons.
And Quantum Icons is particularly designed
for really data or interaction-heavy apps.
The icons themselves are very compact
and very angular relative
to other icon sets.
I've linked below some ways to get them.
But basically, if you're in Figma
and you add them as a library here,
go here, find Quantum Icons,
turn it on as a library.
And I could search...
I tried to use a lot of
synonyms in the name here.
So hamburger, I could type hamburger.
I could type menu,
and I'm going to get
this hamburger menu icon.
So called because it
sort of resembles a bun
with a patty in the middle.
Conversation for another time.
But that is just one other icon
set that you can draw from.
All right, on the web the very best place
to find free fonts is Google Fonts.
So I recommend you become
familiar with this site.
We'll be referencing a ton
of Google Fonts throughout this course.
But one thing that's really important here
is if you go to this website
which is linked below,
you'll have the option to batch install
a list of the top Google Font families.
So you can batch install
50 Google Font families with one click.
You do need to download a
free app called SkyFonts
in order to do this.
But the nice thing about SkyFonts
is you can download on multiple computers,
and it'll sort of sync up
what fonts you have on what computer.
Once you download SkyFonts,
I recommend you then go
over to the Good Fonts Table
which is a lesson in the
future of Learn UI Design.
It's in the typography unit.
But you can go there now,
and you can look at a lot of
the fonts that I recommend
as the very best free or very cheap fonts.
Some of them are part of Google Fonts.
That's the blue F here,
and you can download them for free.
Some of them are Adobe Fonts
which if you have a
Creative Cloud subscription
like to Photoshop, or
Illustrator, or InDesign,
then you also very likely
have access to Adobe Fonts
for free as well.
And then some of them are
third-party, open-source fonts
which you can download as well.
So go grab a bunch of those.
When you've grabbed a font
and you've downloaded
it to install it on Mac,
you go to font book, open this up,
and you can just drag it into
this main list right here.
That's all there is to it.
That'll install a new font.
Now one thing I highly recommend you do
is add a folder for user
interface design inspiration.
So I call mine Good UI.
You can call yours whatever you want.
We'll cover more about finding inspiration
slightly later in this unit.
But the whole idea is you
want to have inspiration
ready to go that you can peruse
and get inspired from
before you actually need it.
Because when you actually
need the inspiration,
it can be very difficult to find something
that kind of does the trick.
So if I just open up the very first site
that I have in my Good UI
folder, it's abstract.com.
Very cool, somewhat quirky site
for a design tool called Abstract.
And the other big thing
that I'm gonna recommend,
this is honestly one of
the most important things
in this whole video
is to download the
extension called WhatFont.
When I click the WhatFont extension here,
I can then hover over
any text on this website
and see what font it's written in.
So this is GT American Mono.
This is Vesterbro Poster, et cetera.
And if I click,
I can actually get a little
bit more details about it.
Oh, it's normal style, it's weight 400.
That's the normal weight.
95 size, good to know.
The color is pure white,
okay cool, whatever.
This extension is available
for Safari, for Chrome,
for other Chrome-like
browsers like Brave here.
And a special shout out
to Learn UI Design student Zack Michener
who developed a version of
this extension for Firefox.
I highly recommend that you
start using this extension today.
And then every time you
see a font that you like
or even one that you don't really like
but you're curious what it is,
hover over it and just
put a face to a name.
The more you can do this,
the more you'll start
building a mental repository
of all the different
fonts that are out there
and when they sort of shine.
And so actually just to pull an example
because I've been using this
extension every day for years.
I can't remember when I downloaded it,
but I don't really think
there have been many days
that have gone by where I
haven't actually used it.
And even yesterday I was
browsing a site called onXmaps
which make these custom maps for hunters
or for people who like off-roading.
And one thing I noticed
is they had these very cool headlines,
and I said, "Wow, I
wonder what font that is?"
Easy enough to find out.
It was Atlas Grotesque Web.
And that was really interesting for me
because I could immediately
think of another site
that uses Atlas Grotesque Web.
Here is FiveThirtyEight, and
you can see Atlas Grotesque Web
for their headlines paired
with Decimal Mono, interesting.
But as you start to recognize
seeing the same font
in different contexts,
you get a better sense of what
that font can be used for.
So just in this particular example,
look, when I make this
font really big and bold
and when I set it in this
really brilliant, rich red,
it has a very different feel
than when I have it be
a little bit smaller
and used for all these different headlines
kind of throughout a site here.
It's just one font,
but you can see that
you can kind of achieve
a slightly different character
by styling it slightly differently.
And this is just one example.
As you become a better
and better designer,
you'll start to recognize all
sorts of fonts across the web.
And that's it folks.
That is all of the things that I would do
to set up a new computer
in order to design
as efficiently as possible.
So take a look at the table below
that goes through all of these things.
I talk a little bit more about differences
between different design
apps or operating systems.
And also like I said,
since so many of these
little tools and things
go out of date so much
quicker than the actual skills
of designing which is what we spend
the rest of the course covering,
I will keep the text
below more up-to-date.
And if you see any problems or mistakes,
let me know so that it can be
as useful as possible for
all the other students.
All right, thanks, and we'll
see you in the next lesson.